Hey everybody בוקר
טוב, Boker tov, welcome to good second day of עומר Omer and
first day of חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. We start today on כ'
עמוד א', Kaf Amud Alef, top of כ', Kaf, top of the
דף Daf 20. And we're dealing with the concept of מתעסק, Mit'asek,
and just to very briefly summarize, מתעסק Mit'asek is, by the way
I didn't even explain the word, it means like to be, I
think it basically means like to be self-involved, like you know, it's
reflective, to be involved. So therefore you're doing one thing but accidentally
something else happens, and it's different than שוגג, Shogeg, which is you're
doing the exact act you intended, you just were not aware of
some of the facts, like the nature of this object or that
it was forbidden or something. מתעסק Mit'asek is you're trying to do
one thing and you slip and accidentally you do something else. Often
an example for מתעסק Mit'asek that I like giving is that it
basically happens incidentally. You're gesticulating and you accidentally hit a light. But
the classic case, you know on שבת Shabbos you turn on a
light, the classic case of מתעסק Mit'asek is that you know, your
hand was going for one thing and you missed or whatever, you
weren't paying attention and it went to something else. How is so,
so therefore I would say than שוגג, Shogeg, it's a different physical
act than you intended. The הלכה Halacha differences are that שוגג, Shogeg,
you're חייב Chayav a קרבן Korban if it's a חייב כרת. Chayav
Kares. מתעסק, Mit'asek, because it was completely like an act that you
weren't trying to do, it's not even associated with you and you're
even פטור Patur from a קרבן. Korban. It's not even like it's
your act. However, the qualification for that is if it's חלבים ועריות,
Chalavim v'Arayos, fats or forbidden relationships, because
you derive pleasure in the experience, you cannot divorce the act from
yourself and again you would be like a case of a שוגג
Shogeg and bring a קרבן. Korban. So that's the basic case of
מתעסק. Mit'asek. That's one that applies with the exception of חלבים ועריות,
Chalavim v'Arayos, that applies בכל התורה כולה b'chol haTorah kulah when you're
trying to do a היתר Heter and you slip and accidentally you
do an איסור. Issur. By שבת, Shabbos, and this is our focus
today, we have the statement אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל Amar Rav
Nachman amar Shmuel
that by שבת, מתעסק Shabbos misasek. is פטור Patur because of not
just a general idea that it's not your act, but a specific
פסוק Passuk that says מלאכת מחשבת, Meleches Machsheves, which means a lot
of things but in this context it means like an intentional act,
a willful and therefore an act that you're trying to do. Because
we have a special פסוק Passuk by שבת Shabbos, what that leads
to is that your מתעסק Mit'asek applies even if you're trying to
do איסור. Issur. You're trying to pick a bunch of grapes and
you slip and you pick a bunch of figs. Or the גמרא
Gemara goes even so far says you're trying to pick a black
bunch of grapes and you pick a black bunch, I don't even
know, black and a green bunch of grapes. So in that type
of a case even so since it's not exactly the act you
intended, even though you're trying to do an איסור Issur on שבת,
Shabbos you try to do picking, you picked a bunch of grapes,
even so it's not the exact act you intended and you are
פטור. Patur. And that is a special הלכה Halacha of שבת Shabbos,
based on מלאכת מחשבת. Meleches Machsheves. And with that we will continue
to focus on today. I should make another point as well though,
although it doesn't exactly work out in the פסוקים, Psukim, generally obviously
it's understood that the first type of מתעסק, Mit'asek which you're trying
to do היתר, Heter, is a more fundamental exemption. It's not my
act at all. שבת Shabbos type of a thing is more of
a technicality and it's like you're פטור Patur in a קרבן. Korban.
At the end of the day you tried to break שבת, Shabbos
you broke שבת, Shabbos, you tried to pick grapes, you picked grapes,
it was just slightly a different bunch that you intended. That might
be an exemption of a קרבן, Korban, but it does not mean
that fundamentally it's not associated with you at all. The problem with
בשוגג, b'shogeg, no well no no no, you're all בשוגג, b'shogeg, no.
Right no, so as long as you're warned, don't pick the grapes
and you
pick, okay so that's an interesting question and I'm not saying that
either. No, because I mean there's מלאכת מחשבת Meleches Machsheves would apply
across the board. But the point is that it's a technicality. You
get off from the punishment but fundamentally it's still considered to be
your act, it's just technically you don't get the consequences of it.
Now the basic, of course, the problem with that is that the
פסוקים Psukim don't work because the פסוק Passuk we learn basic מתעסק
Mit'asek, is from אשר חטא בה, Asher chata bah, that you sin
therein, the thing you were trying to do, but that's a קרבן
Korban פסוק. Passuk. So that sounds like it's the technicality. By שבת
Shabbos, the פסוק Passuk is מלאכת מחשבת, Meleches Machsheves, which seems to
define the basic prohibition itself and seems that it's more than just
a technicality. Nevertheless, bracketing that, the basic point is if you're trying
to break שבת, Shabbos you broke שבת, Shabbos, tried to pick grapes,
you picked grapes or whatever, it's hard to say that you are
sort of like you're fundamentally off, you know, you've fundamentally haven't done
it and there it does seem more of a technicality whereas trying
to do a היתר Heter and slipping and doing an איסור Issur
seems of a more fundamental point that it is divorced from you.
So if let's say, giving my case, they didn't warn you, don't
pick those grapes, saying אף על פי כן af al pi chen
and you pick the other grapes and then you go to the
court and they try to, whatever it is, they try you, right,
you say, "Oh no, but I picked the other grapes." You know
how can, so how can you get off that way, right?
Yeah, I'm not saying you get off from court and you don't
get off from other things. It's like more of a נפקא מינא
nafka mina for like if you require תשובה, teshuvah, okay? I'm serious,
like how much do you feel like if you accidentally by שבת
Shabbos, did the first thing, right, you slipped and you were trying
to reach for something היתר heter and accidentally you flipped on a
light switch, you have to do תשובה teshuvah or not? And the
basic answer is no, it's not even your act and was totally
מתעסק, Mit'asek don't worry about it. Okay? Whereas if I was trying
to pick the red grapes and I picked the green grapes, okay,
I probably should still have to do תשובה teshuvah for that on
שבת. Shabbos Let's move on. Top of כ' עמוד א', Kaf Amud
Alef, מתניתין. Matnitin. מותיבי רבי יאשיה. Moseivi Rabi Yoshiya. So those are
the basic differences between שבת Shabbos. type of מתעסק mit'asek, and another
one, and we're going to focus on a שבת מתעסק. Shabbos misasek
Now again, the שבת Shabbos מתעסק misasek is seen as, as I
said, completely thoroughgoing even for black grapes and black grapes. The problem
is in the משנה Mishnah there were all these debates about מתעסק
misasek on שבת. Shabbos. So the answer of the גמרא Gemara had
been that that was a special case and it'll come up again,
so we'll review it when we see it again. Let's take a
look. מותיבי רבי יאשיה. Moseivi Rabi Yoshiya. So רבי יאשיה Rabi Yoshiya
asked again from our משנה. Mishnah. רבי שמעון שזורי רבי שמעון אומר
לא נחלקו על דבר שהוא משום שם אחד שהוא חייב. Rebbi Shimon
Shezuri Rebbi Shimon Omer lo nechelku al davar shehu mishum shem echad
shehu chayav. The debate of רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע
Rebbi Yehoshua about various cases about doing one thing and trying to
do another is not when it's the same basic type of a
thing, that everybody would agree that you're חייב, chayav, אלא על מה
נחלקו, ela al mah nechelku, what did they debate? על דבר שהוא
משום שני שמות, al davar shehu mishum shenei shemos, two different types
of things. רבי אליעזר מחייב חטאת ורבי יהושע פוטר. Rebbi Eliezer mechayev
chatas veRebbi Yehoshua potar. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says you're חייב chayav
and רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua says you're exempt. Now it's not exactly
clear what two things mean. What two things mean red grapes and
green grapes? What two things mean grapes and figs? What two things
mean two fundamentally different prohibitions? It's not exactly clear how far different
those are, but then רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda comes and says oh
no no no, they even debate between red grapes and green grapes.
So it sounds like the two things of רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
and רבי שמעון שזורי Rebbi Shimon Shezuri are more radically different than
the red grapes and the green grapes. Let's take a look.
רבי יהודה מאי קאמר דפליגי בנתכוון ללקוט ענבים וליקט תאנים שחורות וליקט
לבנות. Rebbi Yehuda mai ka'amar deplitgi biniskaven laket anavim velaket teinim shechoros
velaket levanos. ענבים ותאנים וליקט לבנות ענבים וליקט לבנות ענבים ותאנים שחורות
רמיד. Anavim veteinim velaket levanos anavim velaket levanos anavim veteinim shechoros ramid.
I'm sorry. Okay. ענבים ותאנים שחורות
ולבנות.
Anavim veteinim
shechoros ulevanos. Yeah. Okay. Right. I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
I just put it back up there. So רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
was disagreeing, right, they were arguing on רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda was arguing on them. So he's arguing a case
of ללקוט ענבים וליקט תאנים. laket anavim velaket teinim. You were trying
to pick grapes and you picked figs. שחורות וליקט לבנות. Shechoros velaket
levanos. Why didn't you pick black? So ענבים ותאנים שחורות ולבנות מאי
ניהו? Anavim veteinim shechoros ulevanos mai nihu? So the גמרא Gemara assumes
that what did those things constitute? Grapes and figs, white and black,
שני שמות, shenei shemos, two names. Now of course that's funny because
until now in the משנה, Mishnah, the שני שמות shenei shemos are
two fundamentally different sins, but here the גמרא Gemara is assuming that
that's also שני שמות. shenei shemos. If he wanted to say שם
אחד, shem echad, he would have said black grapes and black grapes.
So
היינו רבי שמעון ורבי שמעון שזורי. hainu Rebbi Shimon veRebbi Shimon Shezuri.
So isn't that exactly the same? So
רבי יהודה מאי אתא לאשמועינן? Rebbi Yehuda mai asah le-ashme'inan? So
isn't that exactly what we just said? שני שמות shenei shemos is
the debate, שם אחד shem echad is not. אלא לאו מתעסק איכא
בינייהו. ela lav misasek ika beinihu. It must be that here's the
debate.
רבי יהודה סבר מתעסק חייב. Rebbi Yehuda savar misasek chayav. רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda says that מתעסק misasek is חייב, chayav, right, because he
says the case of green grapes and black grapes is debated,
which means let me just check רש"י, Rashi, right, רבי שמעון ורבי
שמעון שזורי סברי מתעסק פוטר,
Rebbi Shimon veRebbi Shimon Shezuri savri
misasek potar, that מתעסק misasek
is exempt.
So now what does this mean? You'll remember that yesterday the issue
was how do we explain the fact that in the משנה Mishnah
there seems to be debate about the case of like the black
grapes and the green grapes if the position was that by שבת
Shabbos even black and black grapes is מתעסק? misasek? How do you
explain the case in the משנה Mishnah that it seems that some
people say that you're פוטר potar in some of those cases? So
רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua says you're פוטר, potar, רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
says you're חייב. chayav. So how do we do that? So we
said that was a special case called אבד מלקט מליבו, avad melaket
milibo, when the picker forgot what he was doing. So which means
the following, just remind you of that scenario: it was a case
where the guy said I need green grapes. And at the moment
he was going for it, he forgot what he was out to
do and he thought he wanted black grapes. And then he made
a mistake and accidentally got the green grapes. So at the end
of the day he got what he wanted, but it wasn't what
he was intending. It's like a difference between what you want and
what you intend. At that moment you were intending for the black
grapes, but what you wanted was the green grapes and you got
the green grapes. So that's a special case where they debate. But
if it was really a complete flip even from like black to
black, you would be פוטר. potar. That's what we said to try
and even say that categorically by שבת Shabbos a real מתעסק misasek
everybody agrees you're פוטר. potar. So now the גמרא Gemara saying, okay,
now we have a debate of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and רבי
שמעון שזורי Rebbi Shimon Shezuri about שני שמות shenei shemos and שם
אחד, shem echad, but it seems to be that they're saying the
same thing if we assume black grape and green grape is שני
שמות. shenei shemos. Maybe let's say what they're debating is exactly this
point. That רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon and רבי שמעון שזורי Rebbi Shimon
Shezuri like we said yesterday, they're assuming that a fundamentally מתעסק misasek
is פוטר. potar. Where do they debate? They debate the case of
this case of אבד מלקט מליבו avad melaket milibo where you got
what you wanted but not what you intended and so on. And
then רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, when he talks about his black grapes
and his green grapes, he's saying no, there are even cases of
real מתעסק misasek that some people would still say you're חייב. chayav.
You want to assume מתעסק misasek everybody says you're פוטר potar and
the only case you're debating is the case of when the guy
got what he wanted but not what he was intending. I'm going
to tell you the case of black grapes and green grapes and
so on, that even in cases of real מתעסק, misasek, some people
still say you're חייב. chayav. So that's how. So that's how the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to frame the debate because otherwise it's that
they're saying the same thing. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* answers. לא *Lo*, not necessarily. מתעסק mitasek. דכולי עלמא פטור patur.
*Misasek dekulei alma patur*. We're going to insist like we said before,
that in true מתעסק mitasek *misasek*, you were trying for grapes, for
black grapes and you got green grapes, or not even that, even
black grapes and you got different black grapes. True מתעסק mitasek *misasek*,
you got something different, not exactly, precisely what you were trying for,
דברי הכל פטור patur *divrei hakol patur*, everybody would say you're exempt.
So what's, what are their cases about black grapes and green grapes
and two שמות *shemos* and one שם *shem*? What's this all talking
about? Like we said before, והכא בהכא קמיפלגי *vehaka behaka kamifligi*, here's
what they debate: רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon שזורי סבר שכח מלקט מביבו
בשם אחד beshem echad? דברי הכל חייב chayav, כי פליגי בשני שמות
*Rabbi Shimon Shezuri savar shachach melaket mivivo beshem echad divrei hakol chayav
ki paligi bishnei shemos*, that we're all talking, all this discussion of
רבי שמעון שזורי *Rabbi Shimon Shezuri*, רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* is all talking about the special case of
not classic מלקט *melaket*, of not classic מתעסק mitasek, *misasek*, but אבן
מלקט מביבו *aven melaket mivivo*, that you got what you wanted but
not what you intended. Okay, you remember this? You got the scenario,
you were, you wanted green grapes at the moment you forgot and
thought you wanted black, you slipped and you got the green. So
you got what you wanted, not what you intended. Those are the
cases where you might be חייב chayav. *chayav*, okay? And that's what
everybody is talking about. So the first position said that would be
only that the possibility that you're פטור patur *patur* if, is when
it's, when it's שני שמות *shnei shemos*. Alright, בשם אחד beshem echad,
דברי הכל חייב chayav. *beshem echad divrei hakol chayav*.
If it was black grapes and black grapes, the case of where
you got what you wanted but not what you intended, everybody says
you're חייב chayav *chayav* if it's, if it's black and black. כי
פליגי בשני שמות *Ki paligi bishnei shemos*, they're debating two, two different
שמות *shemos*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda סבר לא שנא בשם אחד ולא
שנא בשני שמות פליגי *Rabbi Yehuda savar lo shena beshem echad velo
shena bishnei shemos paligi*. And רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says no, even
בשם אחד *beshem echad* they debate. Now here what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* seems to be doing, it's not spelled out, but seems to
be willing to admit that black grapes and green grapes is שם
אחד shem echad. *shem echad*, okay? Which is anyway what we would
have normally thought. Your original statement of שני שמות *shnei shemos* if
you remember followed on the heels of things like חלב ונותר *chelev
venosar*, fundamentally different things. So here, without exactly fleshing it out, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to be saying like this, that when they
said the debate of sometimes you're חייב chayav. *chayav* is by שני
שמות *shnei shemos*, pardon me, excuse me, sometimes you are, right, חייב
chayav? *chayav* sometimes you're פטור patur. *patur*, the debate whether you're חייב
chayav. *chayav* or פטור patur. *patur* is when you're basically going for
the grapes and let's say you got the figs. But if it's
going for the
grapes and let's say you got the grapes, even black and red,
black and green, there everybody will say you're חייב chayav *chayav*. That
was רבי שמעון שזורי *Rabbi Shimon Shezuri*. And most when they say
you're פטור patur. *patur* it's when it's something like grapes and figs.
And comes along רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
says no, even black grapes and white grapes, even if it's שם
אחד shem echad. *shem echad*, even there some people will say that
you are going to sometimes be פטור patur. *patur*. That is even
שם אחד shem echad, *shem echad* some people will say you're פטור
patur *patur*. So just to step back again and say what, what's
going on. In the משנה mishna *Mishnah* you have רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* very clear talking about even things like black grapes and white
grapes and he says there sometimes you'll be פטור patur, *patur*, okay?
Even though that seems very similar. רבי שמעון שזורי *Rabbi Shimon Shezuri*
and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* say, say the debate is שני שמות
*shnei shemos* not שם אחד shem echad *shem echad*. How are they
saying different things? So what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to be
saying at the end is black grapes and white grapes is שם
אחד shem echad. *shem echad*. So רבי שמעון שזורי *Rabbi Shimon Shezuri*
and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* say if it's basically two types of
grapes, I don't care black or white or whatever, everybody's going to
say you're חייב chayav. *chayav*. If you're going to be פטור patur.
*patur* when you slip and do the wrong thing in
אבן מלקט מביבו *aven melaket mivivo*,
I'm going to say that in a minute, but let me first
start with the one. Okay, so what, ever if it's all grapes
and grapes, even black and white, that's all שם אחד shem echad,
*shem echad*, everybody's going to say you're חייב chayav *chayav*. If you're
ever going to be פטור patur? *patur*, it's when it's like the
case of grapes and figs. Comes along רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says no, even if it's black grapes and
green grapes, even if it's שם אחד shem echad, *shem echad*, even
there some people will say that you're פטור patur, *patur*. Whether it's
black and black I don't know, but anyway even if it's only
a slight difference like black and green, people will say you're פטור
patur *patur*. Now all of that, שם אחד shem echad *shem echad*
or שני שמות *shnei shemos*, will you be פטור patur *patur* if
you make a mistake, even a very similar mistake, that's only the
special case of אבן מלקט מביבו *aven melaket mivivo* where in the
end you got what you were wanting but not what you intended.
But and where sort of bracketing the entire משנה mishna's *Mishnah* to
be that special case in order to be able to say that
when it comes to real מתעסק mitasek? *misasek*, you were going for
one and you slipped and you got the other, even black for
black, if it's, if it's a real case of מתעסק mitasek, *misasek*,
then everybody would say there's never a debate, even שם אחד *shem
echad*, even black grapes and black grapes, everybody would say on Shabbos
you are going to be פטור patur. *patur*. Okay, so what we've
done is we've taken a משנה Mishna *Mishnah* that seems to try
to limit the parameters of מתעסק mitasek. *misasek*, some cases are debated,
שם אחד *shem echad* or שני שמות *shnei shemos*, and say that's
only this special case of אבן מלקט *aven melaket*, but when it's
real case of מתעסק mitasek *misasek* you're completely פטור patur. *patur* on
Shabbos. Okay, and now as if that wasn't extreme enough, we continue
with other cases of a slightly different than you intended will get
you off the hook by Shabbos. So let's take a look. רבא
Rava אמר לכדן איכא בינייהו *Rava amar lekaden ika beinaihu*. The debate
of רבי שמעון שזורי *Rabbi Shimon Shezuri* and רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
is a question not about, you know, a special case of like,
of what do you call it, of אבן מלקט מביבו *aven melaket
mivivo*, it's another type of a special case. What would be that
special case? Where what you did exactly what you tried to do,
but the order was different than you were intending. Oh wow. What's
the case? והתניא *Vehatanya* as we taught, this is not a question
והתניא *hatanya*, it's a proof, as we taught in a ברייתא braita
*Baraisa*. היו לפניו שתי נרות דלוקות. You had in front of you
two lit candles—or כבויות kvuyot is probably what the right גירסא girsa
is—ונתכוון לכבות את זה וכיבה את זה, להדליק את זה והדליק את
זה פטור. venitkavein lechabot et zeh vechibah et zeh, lehadlik et zeh
vehidlik et zeh patur. So you tried to extinguish candle A and
instead you did B, or you tried to light candle A and
instead you did B. In that case you're פטור. patur. So right
there, that's like the green grapes and the green grapes, the black
grapes and the black grapes. You did exactly what you were trying
to do, you just did it on the wrong object that was
almost an identical object. But it wasn't the object you were intending,
that is enough to say you're פטור patur on שבת. Shabbat. For
שבת Shabbat that's enough of a מתעסק. mit'asek And therefore again we're
saying that that in our משנה Mishna everybody would agree to, which
is why we're trying to limit our משנה Mishna debate to a
more special case. Now the ברייתא braita goes on, בשתי נשימות פטור
bishtei nishimot patur. and now it says, I'm sorry, yeah, it goes
on. להדליק ולכבות וכיבה והדליק בנשימה אחת חייב. lehadlik ulechabot vechibah vehidlik
binshima achat chayav. If you were trying to extinguish candle one and
light candle two, you might also were trying to do it in
the same... so there and you did that, so you're חייב, chayav.
which is pretty obvious. Let's say you did בשתי נשימות פטור.
bishtei nishimot patur. בנשימה binshima is when you breathe, in other words
right with one breath. Right. How are you lighting a candle like
that?
So what you did basically was, so what I... what I was
going to say was as you blew one out the flame sort
of jumped from one flame to the other. Okay, so that's what
you did. So you were trying to light, I'm sorry, did I
jump ahead? I'm sorry,
I'm sorry, so I didn't explain correctly. להדליק ולכבות. lehadlik ulechabot. So
you did the wrong order. You were trying to light and to
extinguish, be that order. And instead, וכיבה והדליק. vechibah vehidlik. You extinguished
then you lit. So you reversed the order. How did you extinguish
and you light in בנשימה אחת, binshima achat, in one breath? One
went out and... but the flame caught on the neighboring one. Okay,
so there although you reversed the order, if you did it in
one breath you're חייב. chayav בשתי נשימות פטור. bishtei nishimot patur, If
you do it in two breaths, so you really do it sequentially.
One breath is seen to be simultaneous, although it's true it happened
sequentially, since it was through one act of breathing it's seen as
the same time. Or stay... two breaths is really seen as sequential.
So if you did two breaths and you really reversed the order
you intended, you're פטור. patur. If it was one breath, so it
was basically seen as simultaneous, then you're חייב. chayav So the גמרא
Gemara says פשיטא. pishita. Obviously you're חייב chayav if it's one breath.
Why is that obvious? No, it's not so obvious. מהו דתימא mahu
deteima I might have thought לא חשיבי מחשבתו lo hashivei machshavto even
in the one breath case you should be exempt because your intention
was not fulfilled. דהא להדליק בעי מעיקרא ולבסוף לכבות. deha lehadlik baei
meikara ulevasof lechabot. You wanted to first light and then extinguish. וכי
עבד מעשה vechi avad maaseh when you actually did it, you breathed,
כיבה ולבסוף הדליק. kiba ulevasof hidlik. You extinguished and then you lit,
you reversed the order. אימא פטור eima patur I would say you're
exempt. קמשמע לן kamashma lan so that's what this ברייתא braita is
teaching me. נהי דאקדמומי לא מקדים אחרומי נמי לא מאחר. nehi deakdumumi
lo makdim achurumi nami lo maacher.
On the one hand you did not do
first what you had wanted to do first. First you wanted to
light, and you didn't light first. On the other hand it wasn't
totally against what you intended because you didn't want to extinguish last
and you didn't extinguish last, you did it all at the same
time. Okay, is that clear? Meaning you wanted to first light and
extinguish and you did it all at the same time. So did
you do what you wanted or not? On the one hand you
didn't do what you wanted because it wasn't lighting first. On the
other hand it was somewhat what you wanted because it wasn't extinguishing
after the lighting because you know, because at the end of the
day it was seen as the extinguishing and the lighting happened at
the same time. Okay, so... I said that wrong. It wasn't that...
did I say it right?
You got it. Okay, you got the point. Okay, so anyway,
right, meaning yes. Meaning on the one hand, let me just say
this again. On the one hand you didn't light first, so it
wasn't exactly what you wanted. On the other hand it wasn't exactly
what you didn't want because you didn't light last either. The lighting
and the extinguishing happened at the same time. So that's close enough
to what you wanted. It wasn't the reverse of the order, just
wasn't exactly the order. That's close enough to say you're חייב. chayav
Yes.
At the same time as the נשימה. neshima. What if you took
two breaths and the same thing happened?
Well, that it says in the next line is בשתי נשימות bishtei
nishimot פטור, patur. right?
So, right. So if you actually reversed the order, if you tried
to do A B and you end up doing B A, then
you're פטור. patur? You really reversed the order, right, because it was
two separate breaths, it's seen as two separate times. Okay. If you
were trying to do A then B and instead you did A
B at the same time, okay, so you didn't get the thing
you wanted to be first wasn't first, but on the other hand
it wasn't last either, it was all at the same time. Okay,
anyway, what do we see from that? And this goes again to
show, this is a great ברייתא braita that illustrates how far we
go by the concept of מתעסק mit'asek, on שבת. Shabbat. Even doing
of the wrong candle is enough to get you off the hook.
That's like black grapes and black grapes. And the most, and not
only that, this ברייתא braita says that even doing the reverse order
is enough to get you off the hook. It was exactly what
you wanted, but just in a different order. And at most there's
a question of instead of sequential it was simultaneous, is that going
to be considered to be close enough that you are going to
be חייב? chayav Okay, and that's what the גמרא Gemara says, that
might be the whole debate going. Now, exactly how we read the
question of order into our משנה Mishna. of רבי שמשון שזורי Rabbi
Shimshon Shazuri and רבי יהודה about about those types of cases, but
a classic מתעסק mit'asek everybody will agree. Now exactly how we read
the question of order into our משנה Mishna seems to be a
bit of a stretch, but anyway,
the way רש״י Rashi says it is that basically it becomes a
question of does order matter בשתי שמות bishtei shemot or בשם אחד?
Okay, and in our ברייתא braita here we see that even בשם
אחד,
well meaning, well let me let me let me let me sort
of clarify. In this ברייתא braita we see that order mattered when
it was שתי שמות, shtei shemot, right? When it was extinguishing and
lighting. There it's clear that order matters and if you wanted to
extinguish and light then you lit and extinguished you're פטור. patur, But
what if I wanted to light candle A and then candle B
and I wanted to do two acts of lighting and instead I
lit B and then A? Okay, that's a question of order and
שם אחד. Is that already so trivial of a difference? Right, it's
in the end I did exactly what I wanted to do, I
did two acts of lighting and I did both candles I wanted
to do and they were both lighting, it's just that the order
of A-B or B-A was different. That's the only question. Order in
שם אחד. So that the גמרא Gemara is saying maybe that's the
debate. Talk about שתי שמות, shtei shemot, שם אחד, black grapes, white
grapes, all those are questions of if it's an issue of order
maybe when it gets to be very similar to, you know, שם
אחד or black grapes and white grapes, maybe there you're still going
to be חייב. chayav? Okay, so what have we said now? We've
said the following: If it's a real case of מתעסק, mit'asek meaning
even if it's black grapes and black grapes, lighting candle A, lighting
candle B, on שבת Shabbat that's enough to be
פטור. Not only that, we also know that on שבת Shabbat you're
פטור if you tried to order if you were doing different things,
lighting and extinguish, you extinguished and lit. What is the possible areas
where we're debating by שבת Shabbat in the משנה Mishna מתעסק? mit'asek.
Two possible scenarios. One scenario is a question of עביד מלאכה מלבו,
avid melacha milibo, you wanted the green grapes, you got the green
grapes, but at the moment you were trying for the black ones.
So you got what you wanted, not what you intended. There maybe
because you got what you wanted that's enough for a reason to
be חייב chayav. and there maybe it makes a difference שתי שמות
shtei shemot or שם אחד. That's one way of explaining the משנה.
Mishna The other way of explaining the משנה Mishnah is is that
it was an issue of order and even though we said by
order you're פטור, but that's when it's clearly שתי שמות, shtei shemot,
lighting and extinguish, and you extinguished and you lit. But when it's
a question of order and green grapes and and white grapes, you
know, and שתי שמות shtei shemot and שם אחד, there maybe there'll
be cases where order differences is so trivial that you'll still be
חייב. chayav? But if it's an order of שתי שמות shtei shemot
or it's a real case of מתעסק, mitasek even שם אחד, even
black grapes and black grapes, one candle and one candle, that is
enough to be פטור. Okay? So again you really see how how
sort of, you know, high the criteria is, how exact the criteria
has to be of your intention when it comes to שבת. Shabbat.
Oh yeah, right, but in this there is no debate in what
רבא Rava's said, right?
In the case of this ברייתא braisa of lighting and extinguishing there's
no debate but that's שתי שמות. shtei shemot. Where the debate in
the משנה Mishnah would be when it was an order of and
with only a שם אחד issue. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
goes on, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now we're going to wrap up
with one or two cases, now that we're done explaining the משנה
and we've explained how hard it is to be over on שבת
Shabbat in quest regarding issues of intent, we're going to have one
or two more cases.
החוטה גחלים בשבת. Ha-choteh gechalim b'Shabbat. Somebody is basically shoveling coals on
שבת, Shabbat, burning embers.
חייב חטאת, chayav chatat, you bring a חטאת. chatat. Okay, why? So
basically what you're going to do is as we'll see in your
act of shoveling you expose some of the coals underneath, so you
cause the coals underneath to burn stronger, so that's a חייב chayav?
of הבערה, hav'arah, burning. And the ones you're shoveling, you're basically maybe
shoveling them and patting them down or something of that nature, those
you are extinguishing, so you're extinguishing the ones you're shoveling and you're
exposing other ones and causing them to burn. Okay, so you're חייב.
chayav. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר משום רבי אליעזר ברבי צדוק: Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar omer mishum Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Tzadok: חייב שתים. chayav
shtayim. You get your חייב chayav. twice. מפני שהוא מכבה עליונות, mipnei
shehu mechabeh elyonot, like I just explained you extinguish the top ones,
ומבעיר את התחתונות, u-mavir et ha-tachtonot, and you cause the lower ones
to burn. So the גמרא Gemara says now now like this: במאי
עסקינן? b'mai askinan? What do we talking about? Now we understood presumably
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says you're only חייב chayav, one, right?
Because this next opinion is you're חייב chayav twice. So what's the
question of once or twice? Okay, אי דקא מכוין לכבות ולהבעיר, ei
d'ka michavein l'chabot u-l'havir, you're trying to do both, you're trying to
extinguish the top ones and cause the bottom ones to burn, which
is what you achieve to do, מה טעמא דמאן דפטור? ma ta'ama
d'man d'patur? Why why do you exempt? Not really exempt, but why
do you say you're חייב chayav. only once? אלא דלא קא מכוין
להבעיר. ela d'lo ka michavein l'havir. So you're only really focusing on
the top ones, you're not trying to burn the bottom ones, you're
only trying to extinguish the top ones. So מה טעמא דמאן דמחייב
תרתי? ma ta'ama d'man d'mechayev tartai? Why you're חייב chayav? twice? The
bottom ones should be essentially an אינו מתכוין, eino mitchavein, I mean
it should also be almost a type of a מתעסק. mitasek, Okay,
now this is actually a little bit funny in the context of
מתעסק mitasek, and I
really
the
גמרא Gemara thankfully does. soft flower bed with your cleated sneakers and
you cause a
furrow, or dragging a bench,
you're trying to move a bench from one place to the next
but you pull it through a soft flower bed and you make
a furrow. Okay, you are trying to do one thing, you actually
did exactly the physical act you intended. Okay, but it says incidentally
another act is happening alongside. Classic מתעסק mitasek. as we've been talking
about is you're going for this and you slip and you do
that. Okay, whether it's an order difference, whether it's whatever אבות מלאכה,
avos melacha, it doesn't matter, you were going for A and you
slipped and you did B. Here you were going for A and
you did A, but as you were doing A, incidentally something else
was happening. That's אינו מתכוון. eino mitkavein. That's what this case is.
You're going to extinguish the top ones, you did it, and incidentally
this other thing was happening, the bottom ones were exposed so they
were burning. So there the גמרא Gemara says if that's the scenario
and that's אינו מתכוון eino mitkavein not מתעסק, misasek, so why would
you say you're חייב? chayav Now of course we know that if
it's אינו מתכוון eino mitkavein and פסיק רישא, psik reisha, if it's
a necessary consequence, you are חייב. chayav So at this stage the
גמרא Gemara is assuming it's a non-necessary consequence. If it happened but
it was not necessary, right, it wasn't a necessary consequence, why should
you be חייב? chayav דלא קמכוין לאהבויי, de-lo kamikhvein le-ahavu-ei, so מאי
טעמא דמאן דמחייב, mai ta'ama de-man de-mechayev, why are you חייב? chayav
So רבי אליעזר ברבי חנינא דאמרי
תרווייהו,
Rabbi Eliezer be-Rabbi
Chanina d'amri tarveihu, so they both explain, here's the scenario, כגון שנתכוון
לכבות את העליונות כדי
להבהב את התחתונות. kegon she-niskavein lechabos es ha-elyonos k'dei le-hav'hev es ha-tachtonos.
You are trying to extinguish the top ones. Now this word כדי
k'dei literally means for the sake of burning the bottom ones, but
רש"י Rashi says that's not what it means, it means although you
are going to burn the bottom ones, meaning you really don't care
about burning the bottom ones, but your focus is on the top
ones. So basically, okay, but it doesn't matter whether you care or
you don't care,
רש"י Rashi reads כדי k'dei here in spite of the fact that
you're burning the bottom ones. Your interest is to extinguish, you're trying
to get coals. As we're going to see, it's talking about a
case of somebody that basically is a
metalworker, and a metalworker doesn't want the flame coming from the coals,
he wants the flame extinguished so that he can actually use it
to somehow you know forge the metal. He wants them as coals,
not as flame. Okay, so your only interest is flame and actually
the way רש"י Rashi reads this is that if something flares up
it's not good for you because it burns away some of the
coal, and you're actually interested in extinguished coals, not coals that are
continuing to be a flame and burning. So the way רש"י Rashi
reads the word כדי k'dei here, I'm not going to get into
how תוספות Tosafos reads it, means just in spite of the fact
that you're causing the bottom ones. So basically you're focusing on extinguishing
the top, the bottom thing is happening, it's an אינו מתכוון, eino
mitkavein, but a type of אינו מתכוון eino mitkavein that's like sort
of like לא ניחא ליה. lo nicha lei. Okay, yes it's going
to happen but you don't even want it. Okay, what is the
הלכה halacha about that? Now the גמרא gemara is going to frame
it not only as we just did, אינו מתכוון לא ניחא ליה,
eino mitkavein lo nicha lei, it's going to frame it in a
slightly different way. Let's look at the way the גמרא Gemara goes.
דתנא קמא, De-tanna kamma, and which one, which
one were we trying to do with all this?
For now, we, well right now it's just interesting because it's related
to questions of מתעסק in the sense that it has to do
with intention. But we have really moved from מתעסק issues to questions
about אינו מתכוון. eino mitkavein. זה וזה? ze v'ze? No, basically just
a somewhat related topic, right, but it's not really anymore about מתעסק.
Okay. כגון שנתכוון לכבות את העליונות כדי
להבהב
את התחתונות, kegon she-niskavein lechabos es ha-elyonos k'dei le-hav'hev es ha-tachtonos, and
רש"י Rashi just says in spite of the fact that you of
the bottom ones. Okay, yeah, what can I tell you, that's the
way רש"י Rashi explains it. דתנא קמא
קסבר, De-tanna kamma kasavar, you want to look at תוספות, Tosafos, you
can look at תוספות. Tosafos. דתנא קמא קסבר מקלקל בהבערה פטור. De-tanna
kamma kasavar mekalkel be-hav'arah patur. The תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says why are you פטור? Because you're מקלקל בהבערה.
mekalkel be-hav'arah. You really don't want the fact that it's burning, that's
actually like being counterproductive to you because it's burning away coals that
you want. Okay, and מקלקל בהבערה, mekalkel be-hav'arah, if you remember we
discussed yesterday, normally מקלקל mekalkel you're פטור, so you're פטור here as
well, it's actually a destructive act.
ורבי אליעזר ורבי צדוק אומרים חייב. V'Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Tzadok omrim chayav.
You are חייב. chayav Why? Because they say מקלקל בהבערה חייב. mekalkel
be-hav'arah chayav. Okay, and therefore right,
we had that yesterday. Since הבערה hav'arah is fundamentally a destructive act,
even מקלקל בהבערה mekalkel be-hav'arah is going to be חייב. chayav Now
what about the fact that you're still a type of a like
a אינו מתכוון פסיק רישא דלא ניחא ליה, eino mitkavein psik reisha
d'lo nicha lei, right?
Does that matter if you are מקלקל, mekalkel, if מקלקל
בהבערה? mekalkel be-hav'arah? Possibly not. Right, possibly the reason that you're פטור
by like a case of פסיק רישא דלא ניחא ליה psik reisha
d'lo nicha lei has to do with the fact of מלאכת מחשבת.
meleches machsheves. And if מקלקל mekalkel you're going to be חייב, chayav
you're חייב chayav even in cases like לא ניחא ליה lo nicha
lei where you don't want it and so on. Okay, so that's
the way we've explained the debate. אמר רבי יוחנן בנופח שנו, Amar
Rebbe Yochanan benofeach shanu, we're talking about a smelter where you really
don't want the fire, all you want is the embers. So what
is the case? אינו מתכוין, eino mitchaven, you try to do A,
you did A, incidentally B took place. So if it's פסיק רישא
psik reisha and it's ניחא ליה, nicha leh, you should be חייב.
chayav The גמרא Gemara says it's לא ניחא ליה, lo nicha leh,
it's a case basically that you didn't want it. So A, it's
לא ניחא ליה, lo nicha leh, B, it's מקלקל, mekalkel, you're פטור.
How about if you say חייב? chayav That's one that would say
that when it comes to fire, you're חייב chayav even by מקלקל
mekalkel and presumably if you're חייב chayav even by מקלקל, mekalkel, you're
even חייב chayav by case of like לא ניחא ליה. lo nicha
leh. Okay, that's presumably the answer. Okay, again, these are hard גמרות
Gemaros to unpack because it does not actually spell it out and
it does not explicitly connect it always to other principles. Let's keep
on going. So the גמרא Gemara actually more or less makes that
point. So the גמרא Gemara. says, אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rebbe Yochanan,
although רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan just got through saying we're talking about
a smelter and seems to explain it the same way, he says,
עד כאן לא נתכלסה טעמה של הלכה זו. ad kan lo niskalsah
ta'amah shel halachah zu. That's like such a nice and it's like
a nice phrase. We still haven't really figured out what's going on
here. Okay, the meaning, the explanation of this הלכה halachah has not
been fully explicated. It seems like there's the explanation that we've given
is not fully satisfactory. אמר רבי אסי, Amar Rebbe Assi, so now
we're going to try again. אמי בר אבין ורבי חנינא בר אבין
דאמרי תרווייהו, Ami bar Abbin ve-Rebbe Chanina bar Abbin damri taveihu, they
both say the
following: כגון שנתכוין לכבות ולהבעיר. kegon sheniskaven lechabos u'lehavir.
So this is by the way,
let's take a look. You were trying to do both, like we
said, straight כוונה, kavanah, you tried to do both. So you tried
to do both, of course you should be חייב chayav twice. How
can you only be חייב chayav once? דתנא קמא סבר לה כרבי
יוסי דאמר הבערה ללאו יצאת. detanna kama savar leh ke-Rebbe Yossi d'amar
havarah lelav yatza'as. There's an opinion that when it comes to fire,
the one explicit thing that the תורה Torah says, לא תבערו אש
בכל משבתיכם ביום השבת, lo tiv'aru esh b'chol moshvoseichem b'yom HaShabbos, since
it's explicit, there's an opinion of רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi that it's
not a מלאכה, melachah, that it's only a לאו, lav, that it's
a negative prohibition, but you're not חייב מיתה, chayav misah, you're not
חייב כרת, chayav kares, and therefore again here חייב chayav always means
חייב chayav in a קרבן. korban. So yes, you transgressed בשוגג be-shogeg
or whatever, but you're not going to bring a קרבן korban if
it's just about הבערה. havarah. רבי אליעזר, Rebbe Eliezer,
what? בכיבוי bachibeuy you are. The תנא קמא tanna kama said you're
חייב chayav once. The next opinion says you're חייב chayav twice. Why
only one? Because fundamentally, it's not because it's a special case. He
would always say by הבערה havarah you're only חייב chayav once. רבי
אליעזר בן רבי צדוק סבר לה כרבי נתן דאמר הבערה לחלק יצאת.
Rebbe Eliezer ben Rebbe Tzadok savar leh ke-Rebbe Natan d'amar havarah le-chalek
yatza'as. That no, it's coming to tell you that you're חייב chayav
for each מלאכה melachah separately, but of course you are חייב חטאת
chayav chatas for הבערה havarah as well. Okay, so according to that,
it's not because of an, it's yes, it's a nice explanation, two
or one, but in the end it boils down to just a
basic question, are you חייב chayav for a fire, okay, or are
you חייב chayav, a קרבן. korban. It's not about the special case
of extinguishing and lighting at the same time.
And what if it's לחלק יצאת, le-chalek yatza'as, even if he wasn't
trying to burn the ones on the bottom, then you're still חייב
chayav for הבערה? havarah? No. Or not even so? No. Whatever the
he, he obviously נתכוין. niskaven. Okay, just נתכוין niskaven makes it simple.
We don't have to get into questions about פסיק רישא psik reisha
and נתכוין, niskaven, whatever. It's just a simple question, are you חייב
chayav, for making a fire or not. Okay. רבא אמר להקדים איכא
בינייהו. Rava amar le-hakdim ikka beinaihu. And this is probably why it
was brought in, because רבא Rava connecting statement. רבא Rava, says the
issue here was, right, remember the case of the candles? It was
לכבות ולהבעיר, lechabos u'lehavir,
extinguishing and lighting. And here too you extinguished and you lit. So
according to רבא, Rava's the issue is that you were trying to
do it in one order, and it happened in the other order.
Okay, you were trying to first, I don't know, light and then
extinguish, and what you actually wound up doing was you extinguished and
you then lit. So you reversed the order of what you were
trying to do. So the second opinion says actually that you would
still be חייב chayav, twice. You did both things you were trying
to do, order doesn't matter. Okay, now, that is interesting because we
haven't seen that opinion yet. We had a ברייתא braisa before that
said that if you reversed the order and they were fundamentally different
מלאכות, melachos, lighting and extinguishing, we had the previous ברייתא beraita said
you'd be פטור. So here though, we are actually getting an opinion,
the way רבא reading it, that you're חייב חייב. chayav chayav. Order
doesn't matter. You were trying to do one order, you did the
other, you're still חייב chayav. twice. And then why are you, you're
חייב chayav twice. What about the opinion where you're חייב chayav once?
Make up your mind. If order matters, you should be חייב chayav
zero. If order doesn't matter, you should be חייב chayav twice. What's
the opinion of one? So the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet says that
it's sort of like the case about the, what do you call
it, of the blowing and them happening at the same time. Because
let me just read the שיטה מקובצת. Shita Mekubetzet. He says,
right, the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet says that yes, that one minute.
Right.
Okay, so he says like this: He says that basically what happened
was, let me just check one more thing.
Right. Okay, so basically the way the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet explains
it is he says what happened was it happened at the same
time. Okay, so if it happened at the same time, still be
חייב chayav twice. And before we said if it happens at the
same time, you're חייב, chayav right? Because at the end, you didn't
really go out of order of what you wanted. So he sort
of says, look, we're sort of splitting the difference. Okay, if you
tried to do A and then B, and they happened at the
same time, we can't be making you חייב chayav twice because it
wasn't exactly what you wanted. Okay, but why don't we say you're
off? And he said like this. You said I first wanted to
do A and then B. We're going to assume that one of
those statements is דווקא *Davka*, meaning either what you were really saying
is I want A to be first, or you were saying I
want B to be second. But you weren't sort of being דווקא
*Davka* that you both want A to be first and B to
be second. So when A and B happen at the same time,
he says one of them is being satisfied. How is it? Well,
I don't know, not really.
Either A was first or B was last.
No, but if they're at the same time, neither A was first
nor B was last. Hold on, let me just see again how
he says it.
Oh, no no, he doesn't say either I want A to be
first or B to be last. What you're really saying when you
say A and then B is you're either saying I don't want
B to come before A, or what you're saying is I don't
want A to come after B. Okay, that's how we're reading what
you're saying. So when A and B happen at the same time,
okay, so A didn't come after B and B didn't come before
A. But then you should be חייב chayav *Chayav* twice? I don't
know. Okay, whatever. Somehow it's close enough that you're חייב chayav *Chayav*
once. But anyway, that's how we're connecting it with רבא *Rava*. Is
that we're saying that you're trying to do one order and either
it happens simultaneous or the reverse order, and therefore one opinion says
it doesn't matter and you're חייב chayav. *Chayav* twice, and the other
said at least if it's simultaneous, it's close enough to what you
wanted that we're not going to say you're חייב chayav *Chayav* twice,
but you're חייב chayav *Chayav* once. Although again it's not exactly clear
how we get there.
Okay, so points out how we actually פוסקים *Pasken* this?
I don't know. איכא דאמרי *Ika d'amri*. Okay, so רבא *Rava*, so
that's explanation number two. So so far, and that's how we tied
it together. So what are the explanations? One is an אינו מתכוון
eino mitkavein, *Eino Miskaven*, presumably פסיק רישא psik reisha דלא ניחא ליה
*Psik Reisha d'lo Nicha Lei* issue. And maybe it's special because of
הבערה *Havara* is even מקלקל *Mikalkel* is חייב chayav. *Chayav*. The other
explanation is it's a straight question if you're חייב chayav *Chayav* for
הבערה *Havara* סתם *Stam*. Because it could just been a question are
you חייב chayav *Chayav* a חטאת chatas *Chatas* for הבערה *Havara*. And
the third issue is it's a question of order. And therefore it
was the, you tried to do one order and it was the
opposite or simultaneous. And therefore one opinion is that order doesn't matter,
which is how we connected it to the previous discussion. And the
other is it matters enough that you're only חייב *Chayav* once, you're
not חייב *Chayav* twice. Now רב אשי אמר *Rav Ashi Amar*, we're
still not done. כגון דנתכוון לכבות והובערו מאליהם vehuveru me'alehem. *Kegon deniskaven
lechabos vehuvru me'aleihem*. Now this sounds pretty much like the אינו מתכוון
eino mitkavein *Eino Miskaven* like we said before. You were trying to
extinguish, you know, and accidentally others, presumably others lit up. So that
sounds like the אינו מתכוון eino mitkavein. *Eino Miskaven* that we said
before. ותנא קמא סבר כרבי שמעון דאמר דבר שאינו מתכוון פטור *V'tanna
kama savar keRabbi Shimon d'amar davar she'eino miskaven patur*,
that says if you're אינו מתכוון eino mitkavein, *Eino Miskaven* you're פטור
*Patur*. רבי שמעון בן רבי צדוק סבר כרבי יהודה דאמר דבר שאינו
מתכוון חייב *Rabbi Shimon ben Rabbi Tzadok savar keRabbi Yehuda d'amar davar
she'eino miskaven chayav*, or some say אסור assur. *Assur*. Okay, now how
is this different than what we said before? Because before we were
assuming that it was אינו מתכוון eino mitkavein, *Eino Miskaven* פסיק רישא
psik reisha *Psik Reisha*. So we had to make a special case
that you didn't want it and that it was מקלקל *Mikalkel* בהבערה
*B'havara* and so on. Here we're basically saying the emphasis of והובערו
מאליהם *Vehuvru me'aleihem*, the emphasis of מאליהם *Me'aleihem* emphasizes that it wasn't
expected. Like you were just trying to be מכבה *Mechabes* and look
what happened, some of them lit up. Okay, like it was, so
therefore it's basically אינו מתכוון *Eino Miskaven* לא פסיק רישא *Lo Psik
Reisha*. It wasn't necessarily going to happen. So רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*
says fine, it wasn't necessarily going to be happening, you don't have
to worry about it, you're off the hook. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
says חייב *Chayav*. Now what does חייב *Chayav* mean? You can't be
חייב *Chayav*, you didn't intentionally do it, you're not חייב *Chayav* as
a מזיד *Mazed*. But you're חייב *Chayav* as a שוגג *Shogeg*. You
were trying to do A, incidentally, unintentionally something happened, wasn't necessary, but
at the end of the day it resulted from your action. It
would know, the furrow got made even if it was not a
פסיק רישא *Psik Reisha*, so you made a furrow. So at least
you're חייב *Chayav* a חטאת *Chatas*. That's רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. אינו
מתכוון *Eino Miskaven* לא פסיק רישא *Lo Psik Reisha*, even so, if
it happened at the end, at the outset you can't be חייב
*Chayav* because it might not happen. But at the end that it
did happen, you're going to be חייב *Chayav*. So in this case
you were trying to extinguish, the bottom ones may or may not
have lit up. In the end they did light up. תנא קמא
*Tanna Kama* says fine, it wasn't a necessary outcome, אינו מתכוון *Eino
Miskaven* לא פסיק רישא *Lo Psik Reisha*, you're פטור *Patur*. And the
second opinion says okay, but at the end of the day it
happened. And even it was אינו מתכוון *Eino Miskaven* and even it
was אינו פסיק רישא *Eino Psik Reisha*, you're still going to be
חייב *Chayav* a חטאת *Chatas* and that's the opinion of תנא *Tanna*.
So that's probably the very easiest way to read that. It's a
simple case of אינו מתכוון *Eino Miskaven*, you were trying to do
A, you did A, incidentally something else happened. One minute, the only
problem that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* has, and that has to do with
the side גרסא girsa *Girsa* of חייב *Chayav* or פטור *Patur*, is
that תוספות *Tosafos* says that normally when we say רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* says אינו מתכוון *Eino Miskaven* is a problem when it's not
פסיק רישא *Psik Reisha*, one of the בעלי התוספות *Ba'alei HaTosafos*, the
ר"י *Ri*, says that that only means it's only a דרבנן d'rabanan
*D'rabanan* problem. That in principle רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* agrees to רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* that you're פטור *Patur*. And when he's, all he's
really saying is that it's אסור assur לכתחילה *Assur L'chatchila*, not that
you're really חייב *Chayav*. This גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* seems to say otherwise.
This גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to say if at the end it
happened then you really are חייב *Chayav*. Yes.
So but why is it not פסיק רישא *Psik Reisha*? I mean
isn't that what happens when you kind of you know shoving them
around? Not necessarily. Not necessarily. I mean you're stoking the fires, I
mean...
Not necessarily. I mean there's a lot of factors involved. You know,
I don't know, it's not always פסיק רישא *Psik Reisha*. It's also
an interesting question about you know how much what does it really
mean והובערו *Vehuvru*? Like if you slightly change the burning of it
because you're moving it around, you know, does it really have to
like catch on flame? How much slightly different burn? But anyway, what
can I tell you? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is assuming it's not
פסיק רישא *Psik Reisha*.
This is the same dispute that
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי שמעון
*Rabbi Shimon* have all through
מסכת masechet שבת shabbat *Masechet Shabbat*. Yes, exactly. Also some of it
has been helped because we have תוספות, we have the מסורת הש״ס,
masoret ha'shas, so there's a lot of cross-references that help us pull
it together. But yeah, that's why this סוגיא sugya that we are
doing today and we did yesterday is like central to issues of
מתעסק and כוונה kavana on שבת shabbat, and it's here buried in
the middle of כריתות. keritot.
This מסכת maseches is almost never learned.
Yeah, but this דף daf is learned by people who are learning
עניין מתכוון. inyan mitkavein. Okay. For now the גמרא Gemara. goes on,
תנו רבנן. tano rabbanan. So now we've got a couple of basic
points. Let's just review them. Number one is מתעסק, even if it's
a real מתעסק, you tried to do A and you did B,
even if it was grapes and grapes, candle A, candle B. By
שבת, shabbat. it's ממש mamash you tried to do מלאכה, melacha, you
did a מלאכה melacha and all of that, nevertheless you're פטור. Maybe
it's just a קרבן korban but you're פטור by שבת. shabbat, By
other cases like you know other types of sins, it's only if
you tried to do a היתר heter and accidentally you did an
איסור issur that it's considered just connected from you. And even there,
חלבים chalavim עריות arayot would be an exception. But by שבת, shabbat,
even one candle to the next candle you're going to be פטור.
Where are there some debates? There's some debates about two special cases.
One is עבד מלאכות מלבו. oved melachot me'libo. You got what you
wanted but not what you
intended. There maybe there're more cases you'll be חייב, שמח ושימש, shemech
ve'shimash, or order. You did exactly what you wanted but you reversed
the order. There also maybe there's a difference, שימש ושמח, shimash ve'shemech,
but it's possible even there even if the only difference was order
that you would still be off. And now we were just looking
at these cases of the coals and whatever where in the end
maybe the reason you're off is maybe the debates are about order,
maybe the debates are about the fact of אינו מתכוון, that the
fact that the second coal lit fire was not what you were
intending. But אינו מתכוון is different than מתעסק. You did exactly what
you intended and something incidental happened as well. Last case. What does
that mean? פסיק רישא
literally means you cut off the head. Basically means if you cut
off the head of a chicken you can't say I wasn't trying
for the chicken to die. Okay.
So if you do something and and a nothing will necessarily result
then it's you don't have the idea of אינו מתכוון. Then it's
seen as part of what you were intended to do. תנו רבנן,
tano rabbanan, last case of this, החוטה בגחלים בשבת, hachoteh begachalim be'shabbat,
somebody is shoveling coals on שבת, shabbat להתחמם בהם. lehitchamem bahem. Now
you are trying to warm yourself with them. This is not a
case where you are trying to what are you where you're trying
to extinguish them and you're a smelter. You're actually shoveling them because
you want to warm yourself. You want to bring them over next
you and warm yourself with them. והובערו מאליהם. And then they lit
a flame. So that you can't say like it's לא ניחא ליה,
lo nicha lei, right? I mean my God they lit a flame
and you're trying to warm yourself with it.
But you were not trying, you were trying to just move the
top coals closer to you. You wanted to warm yourself with it
and the bottom ones lit a flame. Okay. So it's similar like
an אינו מתכוון, but here it's it's a type of a לא
ניחא ליה lo nicha lei at least it seems to be. So
תני חדא חייב ותני אידך פטור. tanyi chada chayav ve'tanyi idach patur.
One ברייתא says you're חייב, one says you're פטור. How could you
be פטור? הא דתניא חייב, ha de'tanyi chayav, presumably we mean on
the ones that lit a flame. Okay? Because maybe the top ones
you just moved them, maybe you didn't extinguish or anything. So the
ones that you actually moved you didn't maybe do a מלאכה melacha
with. But the bottom ones they caught flame. So one says you're
חייב. Why? קסבר מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה חייב עליה. kasavar melacha she'eina
tzricha legufa chayav aleha. That a מלאכה melacha that you don't need
for its own intention you're חייב for its own sake. I'll explain
this. והא דתניא פטור, ve'ha de'tanyi patur, the line of פטור, קסבר
מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה פטור עליה. kasavar melacha she'eina tzricha legufa patur
aleha. That even though it's not needed for its own sake, it
causes it's not needed for its own sake you're going to be
exempt. What does this mean? So this is probably one of the
hardest issues in שבת shabbat. to understand. The difference between מלאכה שאינה
צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha legufa and אינו מתכוון פסיק רישא. eino
mitkavein psik reisha. I will give you the scenario of מלאכה שאינה
צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina tzricha legufa. The scenario of מלאכה שאינה צריכה
לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha legufa is the classic case is you are
digging a hole. You basically are only interested in the dirt. You
want dirt. How do you get dirt? You dig a hole. But
getting dirt is not a מלאכה melacha on שבת. shabbat שבת shabbat?
the מלאכה melacha is digging a hole, which is basically like a
type of a בניין. binyan. So are you חייב for making a
hole on שבת? Shabbos, So that's called a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה.
melacha she'eina tzricha legufa. You were doing the מלאכה melacha of digging
a hole but not for the sake of the hole. For the
sake of something else. For the sake of the dirt. Is doing
the מלאכה melacha for a purpose other than its identified purpose... it's
like the purpose is בניין, binyan, בניין binyan means you want a
hole, and you were doing it for some other purpose. Does that
get you off the hook or not because it's not exactly the
way the purpose of that מלאכה melacha is defined. That's מלאכה שאינה
צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina tzricha legufa. That's a debate. It's also a
debate of of רבי יהודה and רבי שמעון and so on. Now
you would seem that they were connected, right? It would seem that
isn't אינו מתכוון פסיק רישא, eino mitkavein psik reisha, right, a type
of a מלאכה melacha you know like or לא ניחא ליה lo
nicha lei a type of מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina tzricha
legufa.
Can't we explain digging the dirt is basically that the hole is
an אינו מתכוון, I'm not trying to do it, פסיק רישא it's
a necessary part of it but I'm not intending for it, and
it's לא ניחא ליה, lo nicha lei, I'm not interested in it.
So isn't that exactly the same as מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה? melacha
she'eina tzricha legufa? So there's an ערוך aruch that basically says yes,
but according to a lot of ראשונים rishonim it seems that it's
different. It's not exactly clear. Why it's different. It seems to be
different in the following way, and this is maybe somewhat ironic, maybe
not. It seems like if I am sort of aware that what
I am doing is digging a hole. That's not like I'm dragging
the thing, I'm not even aware that it's making a furrow, maybe
it is, maybe it's not, maybe it definitely will be, but that's
considered a total second type of thing that is not the fundamental
act that I'm doing. Okay, that here the no, the fundamental act
that I'm doing is digging a hole, I acknowledge that I'm digging
a hole. So on the one hand you could say that's worse
you acknowledge you're digging a hole, you're more חייב for it. But
it could also be better. How could it be better? Because I
am redefining what I'm doing. Okay, I know I'm digging a hole,
but I'm saying this isn't making about making a hole, it's about
getting dirt. So if I'm redefining it, maybe it makes it less
of the מלאכה, melacha, whereas if it happens incidentally, right, I'm dragging
and necessarily a furrow's going to be made, okay, and it's necessarily
going to be made, maybe I'm more חייב there, because my act
can produce the furrow and that was a necessary outcome of my
action and I haven't redefined its purpose, so maybe it's just a
furrow being made is חייב on שבת, Shabbos. I haven't actively redefined
its purpose. How does all of that apply here? So here what
we are saying is presumably we're saying that the flame definitely will
be made. This is the way רש"י Rashi explains it. You move
the coals, the flame will be made, you know the flame will
be made, but you basically and maybe even you will enjoy the
flame, but at the same time you're really saying I'm not interested
in the flame, like I'm not interested in the hole, I'm only
interested in moving the coals. Yes, it's like the same way removing
the dirt makes the hole, moving the coals makes the flame. Okay,
and even if I want the hole and I want the- or
not want like I was trying to, but even if I'm happy
with the hole and happy with the flame, that's not what I
am doing here. What I am doing here is getting dirt. What
I am doing here is getting coals. And therefore, by saying that
that's not an act of making a flame, not an act of
making a hole, that's מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha she'eina tzricha legufa,
and therefore according to one opinion you're חייב and according to the
other opinion you are exempt. And that is different than אינו מתכוין.
eino miskavein. אינו מתכוין eino miskavein is like you're not even cognizant
of it. Maybe it'll definitely happen, but you're not even paying attention
to it. So that's a case where it could be better because
you're not paying attention to it, but it could be worse because
you're not in a position to redefine it. Okay, so now you
have had a quick primer on all the basic principles of כוונה
kavana by שבת. אינו מתכוין, eino miskavein, מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha
she'eina tzricha legufa, מתעסק, and מקלקל בחבורה. mekalkel bachabura. Okay. So. So
that is an enormous amount of הלכות שבת, hilchos Shabbos, הדרן עלך,
Hadran alach, הדרן עלך, Hadran alach, exactly.
Just step in the box. Exactly.
Now we move on to a completely different topic, as Monty Python
would say now for something completely different, okay. We move on to
so that was like two nice packed פרקים, perakim, one about how
many חטאת you bring, one about the whole הלכה halacha of אשם
תלוי, asham talui, now this פרק perek starts with details about specific
things that you're חייב כרת chayav kares that we don't have a
chance to discuss in other מסכתות. masechtos. So the first the basic
one that we focus on right here at the outset is דם.
dam. Okay which is by the way I should point out ironic
and I pointed this out when we learned חולין. Chullin. But
חולין Chullin deals with all things about eating meat, right it talks
about שחיטה, shechita, it talks about, you know, it talks about בשר
בחלב, basar bechalav, it talks about- it talks about כיסוי הדם, kisuy
hadam, it talks about גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, what you do not
get really in חולין Chullin is a discussion of מליחה, melicha, how
you salt the meat to get out the blood and the problems
of blood. You have like not in the משנה a few lines
in the גמרא Gemara. here and there. Anyway here in the middle
of כריתות Kerisos you have at least an explicit discussion of not
if not how you get the blood out but what is the
blood that is אסור. assur. So let's take a look. Okay, so
אכל דם שחיטה בבהמה ובחיה ובעוף, achal dam shechita bebehema uvechaya uva'of,
so if you ate the blood that came out through the act
of שחיטה shechita the basic principle is going to be the following.
The blood that you're חייב כרת chayav kares for, כי הדם הוא
הנפש, ki hadam hu hanefesh, is blood that the גמרא Gemara, and
the משנה identifies as דם שהנשמה יוצאה בו. dam shehaneshama yotze bo.
The blood that the soul of the animal comes out with. Now
exactly how we define that you'll see it doesn't necessarily mean the
animal died at the moment but just mean not every drop of
blood is considered to be soul blood. Only the blood that's considered
to be life blood, maybe that's a better way of saying it,
life blood is blood that you're חייב כרת kares for. Other blood
you might get a לאו lav but not כרת. kares The focus
of this מסכת is כרת kares and bringing a קרבן חטאת. korban
chatas. So which of that blood is considered to be life blood
that it's כרת kares. or חייב. Let's take a look. אכל דם
שחיטה, achal dam shechita, blood that came out at the act of
שחיטה, shechita, בבהמה ובחיה ובעוף, bebehema uvechaya uva'of, whether it is a
בהמה, behema, you know sheep or cow, whatever, חיה chaya like a
deer, or a bird, בין טמא בין טהור, bein tamei bein tahor,
kosher and non-kosher, so even blood of non-kosher animals, right blood of
a giraffe or blood of a pig or whatever- oh giraffe's kosher,
sorry I don't know why I said giraffe. Okay rhino, blood of
a rhino, blood of a pig, whatever, those that's also going to
be חייב for דם, dam, right which is also interesting about איסור
חל על איסור issur chal al issur types of questions, anyway you're
also חייב for
דם. dam. דם נחירה, dam nechira, נחירה's nechira basically you killed it
without doing שחיטה, shechita, like but
you
basically you
know did... דם עיקור dam ikur which is similar which basically means
you tore out the סימנים simanim and in a way that wasn't
a kosher שחיטה shechita but it still basically killed it. So those
are different variations of blood that comes out when you're killing it.
תוספות explains עיקור ikur a little differently, but we won't worry about
that. דם ההקזה Dam hakaza now the bigger חידוש chiddush here is
blood that comes out through bloodletting. But there we have to qualify
שנשמה יוצאה בו. sheneshama yotza bo. That is blood that the soul
comes out with. What that means the גמרא will discuss.
But would it be like blood on kind of נפש nefesh or
something?
We'll discuss in the גמרא. But basically the first case is although
that's the principle, in the first cases you didn't have to qualify.
That's taken for granted the blood that comes out as you've killed
it and it's dying. But here if you're just bloodletting, now obviously
some bloodletting is not life blood. So it's only considered life blood.
We'll discuss what that means in the גמרא. All of these cases
חייבים עליו, chayavim alav, you're חייב כרת kares if you did it
intentionally and a קרבן korban if you did it unintentionally.
דם הטחול, Dam hatichul, blood of the spleen, דם הלב, dam halev,
blood of the heart, דם ביצים, dam beitzim, blood of, there are
two explanations in Rashi, one says is of the testicles, but based
on the later גמרא it seems very clear it means blood that
forms in an egg by a sort of a forming chick, you
know, so it's a blood spot in an egg. דם חגבים דם
התמצית Dam chagavim dam hatamtzit or if it is blood of grasshoppers
or blood of תמצית, tamtzit, blood of תמצית tamtzit basically means not
life blood. It's blood from the animal, but it's some other type
of some other blood that is not life blood. All of these
cases אין חייבים עליו, ein chayavim alav, you're not חייב. Now let's
talk about it, right? The first thing mentioned types of animals, בהמה
חיה עוף behema chaya of whether kosher or non-kosher and דם שנשמה
יוצאה בו. dam sheneshama yotza bo. The second part some of those
are what it's contrasting it to. Blood of grasshoppers, right, חגבים chagavim
is it contrasted or דם התמצית dam hatamtzit which is basically blood
that's not life blood. But in addition to contrasting to those two,
you also have the case about blood and blood of eggs is
not even of an animal. But the other cases,
I didn't say a mammal, I said animal, but the other cases
about spleen and heart is not so clear why those are different,
right? And there basically is a principle that this is considered to
be דם איברים dam evarim which is
basically if you take a piece of meat, let's say for example,
and you cut into a nice piece of a steak, blood runs
out, right? So that is the blood that is absorbed within the
wall in the flesh or within the walls of the organ as
opposed to the blood that is running through the veins, that is
also exempt. Now it's because it's not considered דם dam life blood,
life, right? But that might actually be but anyway, but that is
the conceptual category. One is blood that comes out of the veins
but is not life blood. The other is blood that is in
the walls of the organ. But I understand that there's still in
capillaries and whatever, it's still part of the same circulation system. But
experientially, especially before you had microscopes and you knew about the whole
capillaries and whatnot, that was seen as different. Okay? So one is
blood that comes out of the veins or whatever but it's not
life blood, and the other is blood in the organs. Now the
question about the heart, what does that mean? Does that mean even
the blood in the cavity of the heart? Right. So the גמרא
will discuss it. The general assumption in the ראשונים Rishonim is no,
that blood in the cavity of the heart could be life blood
and therefore you could be חייב כרת kares and we're talking about
blood that is in the walls of the heart, not blood in
the cavity of the heart. Okay?
So wait, so with the egg though, even though so blood isn't
considered life blood because why not? Sort of like you're saying it's
not an animal.
We'll see in the גמרא. Okay. Now רבי יהודה מחייב בדם התמצית.
Rabbi Yehuda mechayev b'dam hatamtzit. Rabbi Yehuda said you're חייב even for
this non-life blood. And by the way, this is all about חייב
כרת וקרבן. chayav kares v'korban. You might be חייב for like this
non-life blood for a לאו. lav. That might not be debated whether
you transgress prohibition, but is it כרת kares or a קרבן? korban?
Let's take a look at the גמרא. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabanan. כל
דם לא תאכלו. Kol dam lo tochalu. You cannot eat any blood.
לעוף ולבהמה. L'of ul'behema. This is an explicit פסוק. pasuk. Any but
don't eat any blood. שומע אני אפילו דם מהלכי שתים. Shome'a ani
afilu dam mehalchei shtayim. Maybe even blood of bipeds, human blood. Okay.
Now by the way, fascinating point is that when the משניות Mishnayot
and ברייתות Baraitot talk about human blood they do not say דם
אדם. dam adam. As we're going to see in the later גמרא,
the tannaitic sources don't have any queasiness talking about anyway some very
queasy types of statements and we're going to actually have a case
about flesh taken from a human and fed to a dog. Is
it considered food or not and so on. But it's very strange
when it talks about blood that it says מהלכי שתים mehalchei shtayim
bipeds and doesn't say אדם. adam. So some people have wondered, that
some people even thought maybe it was a censor, some people thought
it might have been a medieval censoring because of blood libel, but
that's very מענין דיומא. mi'inyan d'yoma. Blood libel claims, you don't want
to start talking even about the possibility oh it's not אסור assur,
to have human blood, right? You don't want to actually be saying
that.
But obviously this was actually clearly was the original גרסא and although
actually I think they have found that the first blood libel claims
did occur like sometime in in... In ancient Rome, but I think
it post-dated the Mishna. Anyway, it is very fascinating why that when
it refers to human blood, it refers to blood of bipeds, never
says human blood.
We're just saying now it's not a problem to consume human blood?
Right, these are what's excluded from the איסור issur of blood.
So it's worse to have חזיר chazir than human blood?
Yes.
So, דם המהלך על שתיים, dam ha-holech al shtayim, human blood, דם
ביצים, dam beitzim, by the way, you often have human blood when
you get a cut and you suck your finger, right?
Yes, or bite your cheek.
Exactly. Okay, so that is actually not אסור. assur דם המהלך על
שתיים, dam ha-holech al shtayim, blood of bipeds, דם ביצים dam beitzim
of eggs, דם חגבים, dam chagavim, דם דגים, dam dagim, so of
grasshoppers and of fish, הכל בכלל, ha-kol be-klal, maybe they're included? תלמוד
לומר לעוף ולבהמה, talmud lomar le-of u-le-vehema, for birds and for animals
at the end of the פסוק. pasuk. Don't eat blood of birds
and animals. Now, מה עוף ובהמה מיוחדים, ma of u-vehema meyuchadim, these
are, here are their distinguishing characteristics: שיש בהן טומאה קלה, she-yesh ba-hen
tuma kala, they have a light טומאה. tuma. Light טומאה tuma means
they could be considered food and receive טומאה tuma from elsewhere. So
obviously, you שחט shecht a בהמה, behema, you שחט shecht an עוף,
of, it's food and it can receive טומאה tuma when it touches
something טמא. tamei. וטומאה חמורה, ve-tuma chamura, they can be a source
of טומאה. tuma. How? If you have a נבילה, neveila, an animal
dies without being שחט, shachted, it's a נבילה, neveila, it produces טומאה,
tuma, or a bird that is a נבילה, neveila, when you swallow
it at least, it also is a source of טומאה. tuma. Okay,
they have light טומאה tuma and heavy טומאה. tuma. ויש בהן איסור
והיתר, ve-yesh ba-hen issur ve-heter, they have ways of being forbidden like
they weren't שחט, shachted, they have ways of being permissible if they
were שחט. shachted. והן מין בשר, ve-hen min basar, they are a
type of meat. Okay, their blood from something that's flesh. אף כל,
af kol, so those are the distinguishing characteristics. אף כל שיש בו
טומאה קלה, af kol she-yesh bo tuma kala, anything that has a
light טומאה. tuma. הוציא דם המהלך על שתיים, hotzi dam ha-holech al
shtayim, שיש בהן טומאה חמורה ואין בהן טומאה קלה. she-yesh ba-hen tuma
chamura ve-ein ba-hen tuma kala. So that excludes blood of bipeds, human
blood, because humans have a heavy טומאה, tuma, if a human dies
it's a corpse, right, it's מיטמא, mitamei, it's the heaviest טומאה, tuma,
but a human can never be considered meat and flesh and food
that it receives טומאה tuma from somewhere else. Okay, so human beings
only have heavy טומאה, tuma, not light, so they're excluded.
I'm טמא tamei if I touch something טמא. tamei.
No, but that's not טומאה קלה. tuma kala. טומאה קלה tuma kala
here means foodstuff. They're never טומאת אוכלין. tumat ochlin. Okay, so human
flesh would never be considered food to receive טומאה tuma from somewhere
else.
So it's not the blood, it's the flesh too?
Right. But as a human, you're never a source of that טומאה.
tuma. הוציא דם—so hotzi dam that excludes humans. Let's just finish this
point. הוציא דם שרצים שאין בהן טומאה חמורה, hotzi dam sheratzim she-ein
ba-hen tuma chamura, I'll also exclude the blood of שרצים, sheratzim, of
like, you know, like whatever, like a rodent, that they don't have
a טומאה חמורה. tuma chamura. Now, what do you mean about טומאה
חמורה? tuma chamura? There are eight שרצים sheratzim that actually are an
אב הטומאה, av ha-tuma, but even though they're an אב הטומאה, av
ha-tuma, they're not as weighty as something like a נבילה, neveila, they
don't cause טומאה tuma by being carried, only by being touched, and
also they only make the person טמא, tamei, not the clothes that
the person is wearing. So it doesn't have the most weightiest of
טומאה. tuma. So that's how we exclude rodents. הוציא דם ביצים, hotzi
dam beitzim, I'll exclude and certainly I would also exclude like fish
or whatever, I will also exclude the blood of eggs, שאין מין
בשר, she-ein min basar, that it's not a type of meat. דם
דגים דם חגבים dam dagim dam chagavim שכולו היתר. she-kulo heter. And
I'm also going to exclude fish and grasshoppers. I could have also
said because they don't have טומאה, tuma, but also because they're never
אסור, you don't even need to שחט shecht them, you can eat
them alive. Okay, so fish and grasshoppers are never אסור and therefore
it is not a problem. So therefore, all of these things, the
blood is not forbidden. Now, that is different than דם תמצית, dam
tamtzit, which is blood of a בהמה behema that's not lifeblood, that
might be forbidden with a לאו, lav, it's just not כרת. karet.
But these are different things that are not בהמה ועוף, behema ve-of,
these fundamentally there is no prohibition at all for these things, which
is why when you buy fish, you don't have to get the
blood out. Okay, and the only issue would become, but human blood,
is there some דרבנן concern, but these things fundamentally are permitted.